Hodge Family papers, 1752-1937 (bulk 1828-1937)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Hodge family papers, 1752-1937 (bulk 1828-1937)
MS 099
Hodge family
The collection has two separate areas of chronological and geographic focus. One relates to the first two Hodge gentlemen, in the northeastern United States, mainly in the mid-19th century; the other pertains to the youngest Hodge, in New Mexico around the turn of the century.
3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
The three main individuals all have the same name. Hugh Lenox Hodge and his son Hugh Lenox Hodge were both associated with the University of Pennsylvania medical faculty; his grandson Hugh Lenox Hodge was a rancher in New Mexico. The Aspinwall and Woolsey families were related by marriage to the Hodges: Margaret Aspinwall married the senior Hodge; Harriet Woolsey married his son.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Hugh Lenox Hodge (b. 1796) and Aspinwall Family Papers, 1812-1873
Series II: Hodge Family Papers, 1752-1869
Series III: Hugh Lenox Hodge (b. 1836) and Woolsey Family Papers, 1825-1881
Series IV: Photographs and Scrapbook, 1860s-1870s
Series V: Hugh Lenox Hodge (b. 1873) Papers and Photographs, 1882-1937
Scope and Content Note
The collection has two separate areas of chronological and geographic focus. One relates to the first two Hodge gentlemen, in the northeastern United States, mainly in the mid-19th century; the other pertains to the youngest Hodge, in New Mexico around the turn of the century. In the first group, primary emphasis is on correspondence between members of the Hodge, Aspinwall, and Woolsey families. One selection of letters is from Harriet and Caroline Woolsey, describing their trip to Cuba in 1867. Also present are handwritten and typescript unpublished and published biographical materials. Miscellaneous records include family expense account books, legal papers, and cash books. Items related to the Civil War are a scrapbook of illustrated newspaper clippings from 1861, and letters written by Jane S. Woolsey to her cousin Margaret Hodge from 1861-1865. A substantial collection of 1860s photographs, mostly cartes-de- visites, depict family members and unidentified individuals. Most were taken in Philadelphia and New York studios, including those of Sarony and Brady; the Parisian studios of Nadar and Disderi are also represented.
Within the later group of items related to the grandson Hodge are photographs, 1897-1910, depicting ranch life near Silver City, New Mexico. Letters are written to him in his position as chairman on several boards of the New Mexico Cattle Growers Association, and concern topics such as grazing rights on National Forest land. Ledgers and journals from his XSX Ranch, and his Diamond Bar Cattle Co., span the period 1891 to 1937.
Hodge, Hugh L. (Hugh Lenox), 1796-1873; Hodge, Margaret; Hodge, Hugh Lenox, 1836-1881 -- Archives; Hodge, Harriet; Hodge, Hugh Lenox, 1873-1937 -- Archives; Woolsey, Jane S.; Hodge family; Hodge family -- Genealogy; Aspinwall family -- Genealogy; Woolsey family -- Genealogy; New Mexico Cattle Growers Association; Diamond Bar Cattle Company; XSX Ranch; Physicians -- Biography; Medicine -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Cattle trade -- New Mexico -- History -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; Silver City (N.M.) -- History; Cuba -- Description and travel; Correspondence; Photographs; Tintypes
Related Material
Three books and 19 photographs received with the collection have been incorporated into the Special Collections book and Southwest photograph collections.
Container List
- Series I: Hugh Lenox Hodge (b. 1796) and Aspinwall Family Papers, 1812-1924
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Biographical materials (including published biographical tributes). 1812-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Memoranda of Family History (Typescript of manuscript volume, which see). 1812-1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Letters to his moether, Mary (Blanchard) Hodge. 1818-1819 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Account Book. 1812-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Letters from various relatives and friends. 1829-1868 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John Aspinwall: Letters to daughter, Margaret (Aspinwall) Hodge. 1814-1848 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Susan (Howland Aspinwall: Letters to daughter, Margaret (Aspinwall) Hodge. 1830-1866? (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aspinwall Family: Letters to sister, Margaret (Aspinwall) Hodge. 1828-1866? (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jane S. Woolsey (cousin): Letters to Margaret (Aspinwall) Hodge during Civil War. 1812-1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Margaret (Aspinwall) Hodge: Letters from various relatives and friends. 1816-1859 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - George W. Aspinwall: Letters regarding his children. 1856 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Family. 1812-1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memoranda of Family History, dictated by Hugh L. Hodge upon the earnest solicitation of his daughter [-in-law] Harriet Woolsey Hodge. (Holograph manuscript mounted in scrapbook). 1812-1924 (Volume 2)
- Series II: Hodge Family Papers, 1752-1881
  - Account Book. 1859-1872 (Box 3)
  - Legal Papers and Miscellaneous Financial Records. 1752-1810 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Thomas Chalkey James: Letters from and related to. 1789-1835 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Estate of Dr. Edward Barton. 1821-1824 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge (1836-1881): Correspondence and related material regarding engagement and marriage to Harriet Woolsey. 1868-1869 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series III: Hugh Lenox Hodge (b.1836) and Woolsey Family Papers, 1825-1881
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Biographical materials (including published biographical tribute). 1825-1881 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Letters to Harriet (Woolsey) Hodge. 1863-1877 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Letters from various relatives, friends, patients. March-April 1881 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Harriet (Woolsey) Hodge: Letters to father-in-law, Hugh Lenox Hodge. 1867-1873? (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Harriet (Woolsey) Hodge: Correspondence with various relatives and friends. 1848-1877 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Harriet and Caroline Woolsey: Letters to Family from Cuba. 1867 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Jane Eliza (Newton) Woolsey: Correspondence with daughter Harriet. 1852-1873? (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Charles W. Woolsey and Jane Eliza (Newton) Woolsey: Correspondence. 1825-1838 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Woolsey Family (various). 1830-1871 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Photographs and Scrapbooks, circa. 1860s-1870s
  - Photographs (family). 1860s-1870s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (unidentified). 1860s-1870s (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapebook of Civil War Clippings. 1860s-1870s (Box 5)
- Series V: Hugh Lenox Hodge (b. 1873) Papers, 1852-1937
  - Composition Book. 1852 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book. January 1862-April 1866 (Box 6)
  - Cash Book. May 1866-February 1869 (Box 6)
  - Ledger. 1866-1871 (Box 6)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: A Brief History of the Mohican Race. 1852-1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Hugh Lenox Hodge: Photographs. c.1897-1910 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Diamond Bar Cattle Company: Correspondence. 1934-1937 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Diamond Bar Cattle Company: (Miscelaneous Material, mostly undated). No Date (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Composition book containing "Arizona Charlie" written in 1866 at age 13. 1866 (Box 7)
  - Two Composition books containing accounts of camping trips. 1882-1894 (Box 7)
  - Drawing book, containing varous sketches. 1883 (Box 7)
  - XSX Ranch: Ledger. 1891-1937 (Box 8)
  - Diamond Bar Cattle Company: Ledger. 1929-1937 (Box 8)
  - Diamond Bar Cattle Company: Journal. 1932-1937 (Box 8)
  - Diamond Bar Cattle Company: Cash Book (account with American National Bank, Silver City, New Mexico). 1929-1937 (Volume 9)